<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<case-study>
  <title>Harmony Festival Documentary</title>
  <subtitle>Capturing the Spirit of Music and Community</subtitle>
  <date>2025-01-20T10:00:00-04:00</date>
  <thumbnail>/assets/uploads/harmony-festival.jpg</thumbnail>
  <client>Harmony Music Festival</client>
  <services>
    <service>Documentary</service>
    <service>Event Coverage</service>
    <service>Aerial Videography</service>
  </services>
  <overview>The Harmony Music Festival needed a documentary that would capture the essence of their three-day event and drive ticket sales for future years.</overview>
  <content>
    <section>
      <heading>The Challenge</heading>
      <paragraph>The Harmony Music Festival had been growing steadily over its five-year history, but organizers felt they were missing an opportunity to showcase the unique atmosphere and experience to potential attendees. They approached us with several specific challenges:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Capturing the diverse musical performances across five stages and three days</item>
        <item>Highlighting the community aspect that sets Harmony apart from other music festivals</item>
        <item>Documenting the sustainable practices implemented throughout the event</item>
        <item>Creating content that would drive ticket sales for the following year's festival</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>Our Approach</heading>
      <paragraph>We developed a comprehensive documentary approach that would capture both the planned and spontaneous moments that make Harmony special. Our strategy included:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>A six-person crew working in shifts to cover all festival hours across all stages</item>
        <item>Dedicated interview stations to capture attendee and artist experiences</item>
        <item>Drone coverage at golden hour each day to showcase the festival grounds</item>
        <item>Behind-the-scenes access to document the sustainable operations</item>
        <item>Embedded crew members with festival-goers to capture authentic experiences</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Production</heading>
      <paragraph>Our team arrived two days before the festival to document the setup process and stayed one day after to capture the teardown, ensuring we told the complete story. During the festival itself, we collected over 120 hours of footage, including:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Performance footage from 32 musical acts across all stages</item>
        <item>Interviews with 28 artists and 45 attendees</item>
        <item>Aerial footage showcasing the festival grounds at different times of day</item>
        <item>Time-lapse sequences of stage construction and crowd movements</item>
        <item>Intimate moments between artists backstage and fans enjoying the music</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Result</heading>
      <paragraph>We produced a 35-minute documentary that captured the spirit and energy of the Harmony Festival. The film was structured around the three-day journey, but woven with thematic elements that highlighted the community, sustainability, and musical diversity that define the festival.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The documentary was distributed through multiple channels:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Premiered at a special screening event for past attendees and music industry professionals</item>
        <item>Featured on the festival website and social media channels</item>
        <item>Segmented into shorter clips for targeted social media campaigns</item>
        <item>Submitted to music documentary festivals, where it won two awards</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Impact</heading>
      <paragraph>The documentary proved to be a powerful marketing tool for the Harmony Festival:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Early-bird tickets for the following year sold out 45% faster than the previous year</item>
        <item>Social media engagement increased by 78% in the months following the release</item>
        <item>The festival attracted five new major sponsors who cited the documentary as showcasing the values they wanted to associate with</item>
        <item>Applications from artists wanting to perform increased by 60%</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </content>
  <testimonial>
    <quote>Juniper Island didn't just document our festival—they captured its soul. The documentary shows exactly what makes Harmony special, and it's been our most effective marketing tool ever. We've seen a direct correlation between people watching the film and buying tickets.</quote>
    <author>Marcus Chen</author>
    <title>Festival Director, Harmony Music Festival</title>
  </testimonial>
</case-study>
