<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<case-study>
  <title>RedBull Brand Campaign</title>
  <subtitle>Energizing Audiences with Extreme Sports Content</subtitle>
  <date>2024-11-05T10:00:00-04:00</date>
  <thumbnail>/assets/uploads/redbull-campaign.jpg</thumbnail>
  <client>RedBull</client>
  <services>
    <service>Brand Films</service>
    <service>Sports Videography</service>
    <service>Content Strategy</service>
  </services>
  <overview>RedBull wanted to expand their extreme sports content with a series of short films showcasing emerging athletes in urban environments.</overview>
  <content>
    <section>
      <heading>The Challenge</heading>
      <paragraph>RedBull has long been associated with extreme sports, but they identified an opportunity to connect with a younger, urban audience by highlighting emerging street sports that don't always get mainstream attention. They approached us with several objectives:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Create a series of authentic short films featuring up-and-coming athletes in parkour, street skateboarding, and urban BMX</item>
        <item>Capture the raw energy and creativity of urban sports in a way that feels genuine to the community</item>
        <item>Develop content that would resonate with Gen Z audiences across multiple platforms</item>
        <item>Strengthen RedBull's connection to urban youth culture while staying true to their brand identity</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>Our Approach</heading>
      <paragraph>We knew that authenticity would be critical to the success of this campaign. Our approach focused on letting the athletes and their stories lead the way:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>We conducted extensive research to identify talented but lesser-known athletes who were respected within their communities</item>
        <item>Rather than imposing a rigid structure, we developed a documentary-style approach that would follow each athlete through their urban environment</item>
        <item>We assembled small, agile film crews who could move quickly and unobtrusively through city spaces</item>
        <item>We incorporated the athletes' input into the creative process, letting them showcase the spots and tricks that meant the most to them</item>
        <item>We designed a visual style that balanced high-end production value with raw, street-level energy</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Production</heading>
      <paragraph>We produced three 5-7 minute films, each focusing on a different athlete and discipline. The production process included:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Shoots in three different cities (Toronto, Montreal, and Vancouver), each with its own unique urban landscape</item>
        <item>A mix of planned sequences and spontaneous moments captured as they happened</item>
        <item>Custom-built camera rigs that could follow the athletes through complex movements</item>
        <item>Interviews with the athletes about their journey, philosophy, and connection to their sport</item>
        <item>Night shoots that captured the energy of the city after dark</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>One of our biggest challenges was securing permissions for some of the urban locations. We worked closely with city officials and private property owners, sometimes having to quickly adapt our plans when a location fell through.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Result</heading>
      <paragraph>The "RedBull Urban Legends" series delivered three distinct but cohesive short films:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>"Vertical Limits" - featuring parkour athlete Aiden Chen navigating Toronto's architectural landscape</item>
        <item>"Concrete Canvas" - following skateboarding prodigy Maya Wilson through Montreal's skate spots</item>
        <item>"Wheels of the City" - showcasing BMX rider Jackson Torres transforming Vancouver's urban obstacles into opportunities</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>Each film combined breathtaking athletic performances with personal storytelling, creating an emotional connection with viewers while delivering the adrenaline-fueled content RedBull is known for.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Impact</heading>
      <paragraph>The campaign exceeded RedBull's expectations across all metrics:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>The series generated over 12 million views across YouTube, Instagram, and TikTok</item>
        <item>Engagement rates were 3.2x higher than RedBull's previous content series</item>
        <item>The featured athletes saw their social media followings increase by an average of 215%</item>
        <item>The content sparked a 28% increase in user-generated content using RedBull hashtags</item>
        <item>Brand sentiment among the 16-24 demographic improved significantly according to RedBull's internal metrics</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </content>
  <testimonial>
    <quote>Juniper Island understood exactly what we were trying to achieve with this series. They managed to capture the raw authenticity of these urban sports while still delivering the high-energy, visually stunning content our audience expects from RedBull. The films resonated deeply with our target demographic and opened up new opportunities for our brand in the urban sports space.</quote>
    <author>Michael Reeves</author>
    <title>Content Director, RedBull North America</title>
  </testimonial>
</case-study>
