<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<blog-post>
  <title>Behind the Scenes: The Making of Our Award-Winning Documentary</title>
  <category>Production Insights</category>
  <date>2025-01-20T10:00:00-04:00</date>
  <thumbnail>/src/assets/blog-3.jpg</thumbnail>
  <excerpt>Get an exclusive look at how we created our latest documentary project that's winning awards at film festivals around the world.</excerpt>
  <content>
    <section>
      <heading>The Genesis of a Documentary</heading>
      <paragraph>When we first received the call from Ocean Conservation Alliance about creating a documentary on the hidden impacts of microplastics, we knew this would be both a challenging and rewarding project. The subject matter was scientifically complex, visually difficult to capture, and emotionally heavy—but also incredibly important.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>In this behind-the-scenes look, we'll share the creative and technical journey of bringing "Invisible Tides: The Microplastic Crisis" to life, from concept development through post-production.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>Pre-Production: Research and Concept Development</heading>
      <paragraph>Our process began with an intensive three-week research phase. We interviewed 14 marine biologists, environmental activists, and policy experts to understand the scientific nuances of the microplastic crisis. This research revealed a key insight that would shape our entire approach: the most compelling way to tell this story wasn't through statistics, but through the interconnected journeys of the people studying the problem and those affected by it.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Based on this insight, we developed a narrative structure that would follow three main storylines:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>A marine biologist tracking microplastic pollution from coastal communities to the deep ocean</item>
        <item>A family of fishermen whose livelihood was being affected by declining fish populations</item>
        <item>An activist working to change corporate policies on plastic production</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>Rather than presenting these as separate segments, we designed a narrative that would weave between them, showing how their stories interconnected—just like the ecosystems affected by microplastics.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Technical Challenges of Filming Microplastics</heading>
      <paragraph>One of our biggest challenges was visual: how do you create compelling footage of something that's often invisible to the naked eye? We developed several creative solutions:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Custom macro lens setups that could capture microplastics in water samples</item>
        <item>Partnerships with research labs that had specialized imaging equipment</item>
        <item>Animation sequences that could visualize the journey of microplastics through ecosystems</item>
        <item>UV lighting techniques that made certain types of plastics fluoresce</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>We also faced the challenge of filming in remote marine environments. Our equipment had to be waterproof, portable, and durable enough to withstand salt water and unpredictable weather. We developed custom housing for our primary cameras and relied on a combination of drones and underwater ROVs (remotely operated vehicles) to capture perspectives that would otherwise be impossible.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>Production: 87 Days Across Three Continents</heading>
      <paragraph>The production phase took us to 12 locations across North America, Asia, and Europe. We followed researchers onto research vessels in the Pacific, interviewed affected communities in coastal Thailand, and documented policy discussions at environmental conferences in Brussels.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Some of the most memorable moments came from unexpected situations:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>When a storm damaged our primary camera while at sea, we continued shooting with backup equipment, which actually created a more intimate, documentary feel that we ended up preferring</item>
        <item>An unplanned encounter with a group of young environmental activists led to one of the most emotionally powerful sequences in the film</item>
        <item>A laboratory accident revealed a new way to visualize microplastics that became a signature visual element</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>Throughout production, we maintained a flexible approach that allowed us to adapt to changing circumstances while staying true to our core narrative vision.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>Post-Production: Finding the Story in 340 Hours of Footage</heading>
      <paragraph>We returned from production with over 340 hours of footage—an enormous amount to distill into a 90-minute documentary. Our post-production process involved:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>A three-week initial review where our entire team watched and logged all footage</item>
        <item>Development of a detailed paper edit before touching any editing software</item>
        <item>A collaborative editing process with our scientific advisors to ensure accuracy</item>
        <item>Seven distinct rough cuts before arriving at our final structure</item>
        <item>Custom sound design that used hydrophone recordings of actual ocean environments</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>One of the most significant decisions in post-production was to intercut between our three main storylines more frequently than we had initially planned. This created a more dynamic pace and better illustrated the interconnectedness of the issues we were exploring.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>The Visual Language of "Invisible Tides"</heading>
      <paragraph>We developed a distinct visual approach for each of our three storylines, which helped viewers orient themselves as we moved between narratives:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>For the scientific storyline: Precise, methodical camera movements, cooler color temperatures, and compositions emphasizing patterns and symmetry</item>
        <item>For the fishing family: Handheld, intimate camerawork, warmer color grading, and natural lighting that emphasized the human element</item>
        <item>For the activist journey: Dynamic, energetic camera movement, high-contrast visuals, and a more saturated color palette that conveyed urgency</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>These distinct visual languages were unified by recurring motifs—particularly water imagery and circular patterns that echoed both the shape of microplastics and the cyclical nature of the problem.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>Impact and Reception</heading>
      <paragraph>"Invisible Tides" premiered at the Environmental Film Festival to a standing ovation and has since been screened at 17 festivals worldwide, winning awards for Best Documentary, Best Cinematography, and Audience Choice at various events.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Beyond the accolades, we're most proud of the film's tangible impact:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Three major corporations have cited the film in announcements about reducing plastic in their supply chains</item>
        <item>Educational versions are being used in over 500 schools</item>
        <item>The film has raised over $300,000 for microplastic research and cleanup initiatives</item>
        <item>Policy makers in two countries have referenced the documentary in proposing new regulations</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>This project reinforced our belief that documentary filmmaking can be both artistically fulfilling and a powerful catalyst for real-world change.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section>
      <heading>Lessons for Documentary Filmmakers</heading>
      <paragraph>For other filmmakers tackling complex environmental or scientific topics, here are some key lessons from our experience:</paragraph>
      <list>
        <item>Invest heavily in pre-production research, but remain open to evolving your approach as you learn</item>
        <item>Find the human stories within technical subjects—they're your bridge to emotional connection</item>
        <item>Develop creative visual solutions for invisible or abstract concepts</item>
        <item>Build relationships with subject matter experts who can guide you throughout the process</item>
        <item>Consider impact goals from the beginning, not as an afterthought</item>
      </list>
      <paragraph>Most importantly, remember that even the most daunting environmental challenges are ultimately human stories—about our relationship with the planet, with each other, and with our future.</paragraph>
    </section>
  </content>
  <author>
    <name>James Wilson</name>
    <title>Director, Juniper Island</title>
    <bio>James is an award-winning documentary director whose work focuses on environmental and social issues. He leads Juniper Island's documentary division and has directed films for National Geographic, PBS, and Netflix.</bio>
  </author>
</blog-post>
